{
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Probability_Theory — Slot 5 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Probability_Theory — Slot 5",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>When a coin is tossed, the probability of getting a Head is p, 0 &lt; p &lt; 1. Let N be the random variable denoting the number of tosses till the first Head appears, including the toss where the Head appears. Assuming that successive tosses are independent, the expected value of N is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{1}{p}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{1}{(1 - p)}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{1}{p^{2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{1}{(1 - p^{2})}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{1}{p}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3561/gate2006-it-22\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>In a certain town, the probability that it will rain in the afternoon is known to be 0.6. Moreover, meteorological data indicates that if the temperature at noon is less than or equal to \\(25^{\\circ}C\\), the probability that it will rain in the afternoon is 0.4. The temperature at noon is equally likely to be above \\(25^{\\circ}C\\), or at/below \\(25^{\\circ}C\\). What is the probability that it will rain in the afternoon on a day when the temperature at noon is above \\(25^{\\circ}C\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.6</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0.8</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0.9</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>0.8</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3538/gate2006-it-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>For each element in set of size 2n, an unbiased coin is tossed. The 2n coin tossed\nare independent. An element is chosen if the corresponding coin toss were head.\nThe probability that exactly n elements are chosen is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{\\binom{2n}{n}}{4^{n}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{\\binom{2n}{n}}{2^{n}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{\\binom{2n}{n}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{\\binom{2n}{n}}{4^{n}}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/982/gate2006-21#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>In a communication network, a packet of length L bits takes link \\(L_1\\) with a probability of \\(p_1\\) or link \\(L_2\\) with a probability of \\(p_2\\). Link \\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) have bit error probability of \\(b_1\\) and \\(b_2\\) respectively. The probability that the packet will be received without error via either \\(L_1\\) or \\(L_2\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((1 - b_1)^Lp_1 + (1 - b_2)^Lp_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\([1 - (b_1 + b_2)^L]p_1p_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((1 - b_1)^L (1 - b_2)^Lp_1p_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(1 - (b_1^Lp_1 + b_2^Lp_2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((1 - b_1)^Lp_1 + (1 - b_2)^Lp_2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3837/gate2005-it-74\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>An unbiased coin is tossed repeatedly until the outcome of two successive tosses is the same. Assuming that the trials are independent, the expected number of tosses is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>6</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3778/gate2005-it-32\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>A bag contains 10 blue marbles, 20 green marbles and 30 red marbles. A marble is drawn from the bag, its colour recorded and it is put back in the bag. This process is repeated 3 times. The probability that no two of the marbles drawn have the same colour is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{1}{36}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{1}{6}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{1}{4}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{1}{3}\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{1}{6}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3745/gate2005-it-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A random bit string of length n is constructed by tossing a fair coin n times and setting a bit to 0 or 1\ndepending on outcomes head and tail, respectively. The probability that two such randomly\ngenerated strings are not identical is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1/2^{n}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1-1/n</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1/n!</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(1-(1/2^{n})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(1-(1/2^{n})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1177/gate2005-52#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Box P has 2 red balls and 3 blue balls and box Q has 3 balls and 1 blue ball. A ball is selected as\nfollows: (i) select a box (ii) choose a ball from the selected box such that each ball in the box is\nequally likely to be chosen. The probabilities of selecting boxes P and Q are 1/3 and 2/3 respectively.\nGiven that a ball selected in the above process is a red ball, the probability that it came from the box\nP is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(4/19\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(5/19\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2/9\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(19/30\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(4/19\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1176/gate2005-51#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Let f(x) be the continuous probability density function of a random variable X.\nThe probability that \\(a \\lt X \\leq b\\), is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>f(b-a)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>f(b)-f(a)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\int_{a}^{b}f(x)dx\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\int_{a}^{b}xf(x)dx\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\int_{a}^{b}f(x)dx\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1162/gate2005-12#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(X\\) and \\(Y\\) be two exponentially distributed and independent random variables with mean \\(\\alpha \\text{ and }\\beta\\), respectively. If \\(Z=min(X,Y)\\), then the mean of \\(Z\\) is given by <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{1}{\\alpha + \\beta}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\min (\\alpha, \\beta)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{\\alpha\\beta}{\\alpha + \\beta}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\alpha + \\beta\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{\\alpha\\beta}{\\alpha + \\beta}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3676/gate2004-it-33\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>In a population of N families, 50% of the families have three children, 30% of the families have two children and the remaining families have one child. What is the probability that a randomly picked child belongs to a family with two children? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{3}{23}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{6}{23}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{3}{10}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{3}{5}\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{6}{23}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3642/gate2004-it-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Two n bit binary strings, S1 and S2, are chosen randomly with uniform probability. The probability that the Hamming distance between these strings (the number of bit positions where the two strings differ) is equal to d is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(^nC_d/2^{n}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(^nC_d/2^{d}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(d/2^{n}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(1/2^{d}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(^nC_d/2^{n}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1072/gate2004-78#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>An examination paper has 150 multiple choice questions of one mark each, with each question having\nfour choices. Each incorrect answer fetches -0.25 marks. Suppose 1000 students choose all their\nanswers randomly with uniform probability. The sum total of the expected marks obtained by all\nthese students is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2550</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>7525</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>9375</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>9375</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1068/gate2004-74#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>If a fair coin is tossed four times. What is the probability that two heads and two tails will result? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3/8</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1/2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>5/8</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2/4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>3/8</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1022/gate2004-25#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>A program consists of two modules executed sequentially. Let f1(t) and f2(t)\nrespectively denote the probability density functions of time taken to execute the\ntwo modules. The probability density function of the overall time taken to execute\nthe program is given by <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f_{1}(t)+f_{2}(t)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\int_{0}^{t}f_{1}(x)f_{2}(x)dx\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\int_{0}^{t}f_{1}(x)f_{2}(t-x)dx\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>max{\\(f_{1}(t),f_{2}(t)\\)\n}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\int_{0}^{t}f_{1}(x)f_{2}(t-x)dx\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/948/gate2003-60#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}